Education and training can help you feel more confident
and enable you to achieve successful catheterization.
You can use this step-by-step video as support
and follow up on any training provided.
Always follow the advice and instructions
provided by a clinician which are tailored
to your individual medical and lifestyle needs.
So what is intermittent catheterization?
Intermittent catheterization helps empty your bladder when
your body can't do it on its own.
It involves emptying your bladder regularly
with a hollow tube with drainage holes, a catheter.
The catheter is inserted in your urethra,
which is the tube between the bladder and the exit,
allowing the urine to flow down the catheter and out.
Let's briefly go through the body parts
involved in the urinary system.
Kidney.
Your kidneys are two small bean shaped organs
that clean your blood and make urine.
Ureter.
The ureters are thin tubes
that carry urine from the kidneys down to the bladder.
Bladder.
The bladder is a hollow stretchy organ in your
lower belly that stores urine.
Urethra.
The urethra is the tube
that carries urine from the bladder out of the body.
And finally, the urethral opening.
It is quite usual to feel a little anxious
or worried when starting something new for the first time.
But with practice and support,
you will soon become more confident
with intermittent catheterization
and it will soon become a natural part
of your daily routine.
Now let's talk through how to use LoFric Elle Pro step-by-step.
Start by washing your hands thoroughly with soap and water.
You can also use cleansing wipes
if you don't have access to running water.
Cleanse your hands again after catheterization.
Open the upper lid.
Hold the catheter in one hand
and gently bend the upper part to open.
Pull the catheter out.
Connect the container to the catheter with a gentle twist,
making sure the arrow on the container points down.
LoFric Elle Pro is an intermittent catheter
with a unique L-shaped handle
that helps you confidently locate the urethra.
Sitting on the toilet is ideal for doing IC,
but if not possible,
your clinician will help you find a position
that suits you best.
Tilt your pelvis upwards and spread your labia.
Hold the handle with your dominant hand gently
and slowly guide the catheter into the urethra.
The urethral entrance is small and sometimes hard to see.
And using a mirror can help.
It is just above the vaginal opening and below the clitoris.
It is close to the anus.
So keeping clean is important to prevent infection.
Once urine starts to flow,
the catheter is in the right place.
Gently insert a little further
to ensure it's fully in your bladder.
Wait until urine flow stops.
LoFric Elle Pro allows for complete bladder emptying.
Now slowly withdraw the catheter.
The unique LoFric surface coating will ensure
that the catheter remains smoothly lubricated.
Put the catheter back inside the container.
Remember, LoFric Elle Pro is a urinary catheter designed
to be used one time only.
Dispose or carry it in your bag until disposal.
Please note the lower container is recyclable.
How often you catheterize will vary individually
and also depend upon fluid intake.
Your clinician will advise you
on the right regime for you.
LoFric Elle Pro is your versatile single use
intermittent catheter ready for you,
whatever your lifestyle needs.